JOE: Processing everyday sensory
information can be a problem
for individuals with autism as
they may be oversensitive, known
as ‘hypersensitive’, or under
sensitive, known as ‘hyposensitive’
or even both, at different times.
These differences in their senses can
affect how they feel, or act and can
have a profound effect on their lives.
BETH: Individuals who have problems
with their vision may, if they are
under sensitive, have poor depth
perception, causing clumsiness or
have peripheral vision problems.
If they are oversensitive, they may
need to focus on a detail rather than
the whole thing and they may have
trouble being in rooms with bright
light such as fluorescents, or even
sleeping without complete darkness.
JOE: If an individual has under
sensitivity to sounds, they may not
respond to verbal communication, they
might enjoy crowded noisy rooms or
bang doors and objects for stimulation.
An oversensitivity to sound can mean
that sounds seem magnified, distorted
or confused and the individuals
can have difficulties concentrating
because they are distracted.
BETH: Every day smells can be
problematic for Individuals who are
under sensitive they cannot tell what
things are, whether they are safe to
drink or eat and they can fail to notice
extreme odours such as body odour.
Those who are oversensitive dislike
strong smelling products like cleaning
products, cat and dogs, and even
perfumes, shampoos and deodorants.
They may also dislike the
smells of foods and cooking.
JOE: Some individuals with autism may have
a restricted diet due to taste issues.
If under sensitive, they may eat
things that aren’t edible and shouldn’t
be eaten or really spicy food.
If over sensitive, they might find
most things too strong and overpowering
choosing to only eat bland foods.
GREEN: Problems with touch can
manifest in different ways.
Individuals who are under sensitive maybe
having a high pain threshold and be unable
to feel things, such as food in the mouth.
Individuals with over sensitivity
may find textures of certain
foods or clothing intolerable.
They may find being touched
painful and have difficulties
washing or brushing their hair.
Each individual with autism has
their own sensory issues and these
can impact greatly on their lives
and the way people perceive them.